Rhiannon: The Care Programme Approach
is a package of care that may be
used to plan mental healthcare and
is there to support young people’s
recovery from mental illness.
It is a framework used to assess young
people’s needs, and make sure that
they have the correct support for
those needs from specialist teams of
mental health professionals such as
mental health nurses and psychiatrists.
Leah: Different mental health
services will have policies about
who is able to get help under CPA
and a care coordinator will monitor
that care and support with regular
reviews, to see if needs have changed
and a crisis plan must be included.
A CPA aims to support mental health
recovery by helping an individual to
understand their strengths, goals,
support needs, and difficulties.
It should be available if a child
or young person has a wide range
of needs from different services
or are thought to be a high risk.
A child or young person may get help or
be offered support under a CPA if they
have a severe mental disorder, are at risk
of suicide, self-harm or harm to others.
They may also be eligible if they neglect
themselves, are vulnerable due to various
reasons or misuse drugs and alcohol.
Rhiannon: There are other things that
may qualify them such as needing the
support of a carer or having their own
caring responsibilities or having been
detained under the mental health act.
They may also get help if they have
recently been put in touch with a
crisis team, have physical health
problems or disability, housing
problems or ethnicity issues.
Local teams will have their own
policies, but these will be closely
linked to the general guidelines.
Leah: Young people who have been
detained under the Mental Health Act
will be supported through the CPA after
they are discharged from hospital.
A care plan is drawn up and this a
written plan of how their care needs
will be met including information about
treatment and any other areas of their
life that may need supporting, such
as housing, education or employment.
Rhiannon: Other things likely to be
considered are personal circumstances,
medication, therapy, physical health
needs, problems with drugs and alcohol and
any risks of harm to themselves or others.
A multi-disciplinary approach will
be used to assess needs and make the
care plan and a copy of this plan
will be available for the individual
or a parent or carer if they wish.
It will also have full details of
what to do in a crisis and once a
young person turns 17 and they need
to move to adult services this will
be planned as part of their care plan.